-==www.RagBear.com==-
是, 首相  第1季第6集
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
-=破烂熊字幕组=-
翻译: angel_liu
校对: tpring
时间轴: T-boy
民主之胜
昨夜酒会上 美国大使
I got some frightful pressure from the American ambassador
向我施加了可怕的压力
at that drinkies do last night.
啊      他们听说我要取消三叉戟订单
Ah.        They'd heard about my cancelling Trident.
啊
Ah.
好像国防工业是
The American defence industries are
美国总统政党的金库
big contributors to the President Party funds.
啊      他说我们在东也门有大问题了
Ah.        He said we had a big problem in East Yemen.
啊?
Ah?
别这样"啊"来"啊"去的 伯纳 我又不是医生
Stop saying ''ah'' like that, Bernard. I'm not your doctor.
对不起 首相      东也门的这个大问题是什么?
I'm sorry.        What is this big problem?
啊...
Ah...
谢谢 伯纳       我去想办法查
Thank you, Bernard.        I'll try to find out.
他好像提了圣乔治岛
He muttered about St George's Island.
圣乔治岛?
St George's Island?
是的 当真有个圣乔治岛?
Yes. There is a St George's Island,isn`t there?
有 在英联邦
Yes, it's in the Commonwealth.
啊 知道了 那个圣乔治岛
Ah, I see, yes. That St George's Island.
他担心共产党想要夺取它
Apparently, he's afraid Communists might try to grab it.
您怎么回答?
What did you say?
我说我要咨询外交部      他怎么说?
I said I'd ask the Foreign Office.        What did he say?
白宫认为外交部
The White House thinks the Foreign Office
都是些左倾分子和卖国贼
is full of pinkos and traitors.
不是的 呃 不全是
No, it's not. Well, not full.
他们不想让红军取得
They don't want the Reds to get
圣乔治岛这样的战略基地
a strategic base like St George's Island.
他说要对英国对美出口征收关税
He spoke about putting tariffs on British exports to the USA
对美国对英投资征税
and taxing US investment to Britain,
以引起挤兑英镑的热潮
causing a run on the pound.
您下午要会见外交部长
Well, you are seeing the Foreign Secretary this afternoon.
不能让他解决吗?
Can't you get the Foreign Secretary to sort it out?
毕竟他们在我们这边
After all, they are on our side.
谁?      美国人
Who are?        The Americans.
我还以为你说外交部
I thought you meant the Foreign Office.
外交部在担心什么 迪克
What's the Foreign Office worried about then,  Dick?
外交部长全听你的吧?
Have you got the Foreign Secretary eating out of your hand.
没错 管教得非常好
Oh, yes. Completely house-trained.
那还有什么问题?
So what is the problem?
问题是首相
The Prime Minister's the problem.
他开始不相信外交部长的意见了
He's starting to mistrust our advice.
他甚至质疑外交部的政策      不会吧
He even questioned Foreign Office policy.        Surely not!
我们甚至感觉到内阁
We even see a danger the Cabinet
自行制定外交政策的危险
may pursue its own foreign policy.
但那太荒谬了
But that's absurd.
一个国家不能有两个外交政策
The country can't have two foreign policies
没错 而且首相
Quite. And the PM's getting
太急于讨好白宫了
far too keen on keeping the White House happy.
天哪天哪 有什么要帮忙的?
Dear, oh, dear. So, how can I help?
现在发生了些事
There are a couple of things coming up
需要指导他一下
where he might need guiding in the right direction.
其中一个是圣乔治岛      啊 对对对
One is St George's Island.        Ah. Oh, yes, yes, yes.
能提醒我一下吗? 迪克
Remind me, would you, Dick?
如你所知 这是位于印度洋的少数几个
As you know, it's one of the few islands in the Indian Ocean
独立后仍属于英联邦的岛屿之一
to stay in the Commonwealth after the Independence.
啊 对 没错 很民主 是吧?
Oh, yes, that's right. It's quite democratic.
是的 自由选举之类的
Yes. Free elections and everything.
但山林中有群左翼游击队
But there's a group of Marxist guerrillas in the mountains.
我们收到情报 他们预谋发动政变
We are getting reports that they're planning a coup.
这些事总会发生的
Well, these things will happen.
他们并不打算自己发起
They're not thinking of starting it on their own.
东也门会提供援助
East Yemen is helping.
东也门不是民主国家吗?
Isn't that a democracy?
全称是东也门人民民主共和国
People's Democratic Republic of East Yemen.
知道了 左翼独裁政权
Oh, I see. It's a Communist dictatorship.
那些游击队是由苏维埃援助的吗?
And the guerrillas are Soviet-backed, aren`t they?
是 利比亚也在背后支援
Yes, and Libyan-backed.
所以外交部明显打算置身事外
Obviously, we in the Foreign Office are staying right out of it.
是的 很明显
Obviously.
我们参与 也只会扰乱几个非洲锋线国家而已
It would only upset a load of frontline African states.
而我们现在还不想对抗苏维埃
And we don't want to antagonise the Soviets.
正是 而且我们刚签了份大合约
Quite. And we've just landed a huge contract
要在圣乔治岛建设机场和港口
to build a new St George's airport and harbour.
一旦站错立场 就会失去这份合约
If we back the wrong side, we may lose it.
我们不介意哪边赢 民主政党还是马克思主义者?
We don't mind which side wins,the democrats or the Marxists?
为何要介意呢? 但还是有问题
Why should we? But you see the problem.
如果首相的丘吉尔式爱国心大爆发
If the PM gets into one of his ghastly patriotic Churchillian moods,
他会干预的
he may intervene.
那些向英国看齐 捍卫民主的废话
All that pro-British, defending democracy nonsense.
我知道 我知道
Oh, I know, I know.
他必须了解一旦你着手
He must understand that once you start
干预别国内部争端
interfering in the internal squabbles of other countries,
你就岌岌可危了
you're on a very slippery slope.
连外交部长都明白
Even the Foreign Secretary's grasped that.
另一个问题是什么?
Really? So what was the other point?
阿拉伯已经提出议案
The Arabs have put down a motion
要联合国谴责以色列
at the United Nations condemning Israel.
我们当然投票支持阿拉伯      当然
Naturally, we'll vote on the Arab side.        Naturally.
但我想首相要我们弃权
But I gather the PM wants us to abstain.
怎么可以! 为什么?
Surely not! Why?
说这次是巴解组织挑事
Something about the PLO starting it this time,
双方都有错 感情用事
faults on both sides. Sentimental nonsense.
拍美国马屁 一如往常
Sucking up to the Americans, as always.
只需让他知道
Just help him to realise that,
牵涉到外交事务时
as far as foreign affairs are concerned,
他的工作仅限于公关接待
his job is to confine himself to the hospitality
热情好客
and ceremonial role.
我尽力
I'll do my best,
但你知道政客进入10号会怎样
but you know what happens when politicians get into Number 10.
他们想在世界舞台上占个位置
They want their place on the world stage.
站在舞台上的是演员
People on stages are called actors.
他们只需作稳健状
All they're required to do is look plausible,
保持清醒 按部就班念台词
stay sober and say the lines they're given in the right order
一些人试图自己想词
Some of them try to make up their own lines
立刻就下台了
They don't last long.
昨晚美国大使和我私下谈了谈
The American ambassador had a word with me last night.
关于什么?      你对圣乔治岛了解多少?
About what?       What do you know about St George's Island?
您对它了解多少?
What do you know about it?
外交部长是你 不是我
Well, you're the Foreign Secretary, not me!
有左翼接管的危险吗?
Is there any danger of a Communist takeover?
呃 他说有吗?      他暗示有
Well, did he say there was?        He hinted.
不 绝不可能
No. No chance at all. No chance at all.
不然外交部会告诉我的
The Foreign Office would have told me.
你肯定他们什么都告诉你?
You're sure they always tell you everything?
只要他们认为我该知道的
Well, everything they think I should know.
我就怕这个
That's what I'm afraid of.
美国人很担心
The Americans are worried
我们现在不能惹他们
and we can't afford to upset them at the moment.
我们肯定已经控制了事态
I'm sure we've got everything under control.
张伯伦还以为控制了希特勒呢
Chamberlain thought Hitler was under control.
张伯伦
Ah, well, Chamberlain.
艾登还以为控制了纳塞尔呢
Eden thought Nasser was under control.
外交部不知道自己在做什么?
The F.O. doesn't know what it's doing?
不 他们不交待他们在做什么
No, they don't tell us what they're doing!
可笑 他们详细回答我提出的每个问题
Absurd. They give me a full answer to any questions I ask.
你没问的呢?      例如?
And the ones you don't ask?        Such as?
例如圣乔治岛
Such as about St George's Island.
我不问这些问题
Ah, well, I don't ask those.
问问他们 帮我个忙 行吗?
Well, just ask them. For me. All right?
当然 您非要问的话
Yes, of course. If that is what you want
但别忘了
But don`t foget.
一旦您干预别国内部争端
Once you interfere in other countries' internal squabbles,
您就岌岌可危了
you're on a very slippery slope.
还有什么?
Anything else?
有 据说我们今晚要在联合国投票
Yes, I gather we're proposing to vote against
反对以色列 为什么?
Israel in the UN tonight. Why?
他们炸了巴解组织
They bombed the PLO.
巴解组织也炸了以色列
The PLO bombed Israel.
但以色列炸弹扔得比较多
But the Israelis dropped more bombs than the PLO!
巴解组织挑头
The PLO started it!
不 他们没有
No, they didn't.
我看双方都有错
It seems to me there are faults on both sides.
我的消息不是这样的
Not according to my advice.
美国很忧虑 想要我们弃权
America is worried. They want us to abstain.
我觉得我们不能
I don't think we could do that.
怎么?      外交部不会同意的
Why not?        The Foreign Office wouldn't wear it.
是他们听我们的
Are they here to follow our instructions or
还是我们听他们的?
are we to follow theirs?
别傻了
Now, don't be silly.
首相 汉弗莱爵士到了
Prime Minister, Sir Humphrey's here.
首相      汉弗莱 我很担心
Prime Minister.        Humphrey, I'm worried.
什么事 首相?
Oh, what about, Prime Minister?
美国人
About the Americans.
对 我们都担心美国人
Well, we're all worried about the Americans.
外交是门复杂营生 对吗?
Foreign affairs are a complicated business,aren`t they?
没错 首相 所以扔给外交部处理
Yes,That's why we leave it to the Foreign Office.
将来几个月我得跟美国搞好关系
I've got to keep in with the Americans for the next few months
为取消大额国防订单打基础
if I'm to cancel our defence order.
昨晚我猜他们也很担心我们
Ah. I gather that they're worried about us.
他们当然担心 不过我知道怎样与他们搞好关系
Of course they are, but I know how to keep in with them.
怎样?       别取消大额国防订单
How?        Don't cancel the huge defence order.
不 汉弗莱 我决定了
No, Humphrey, I'm determined on that,
但别的方面不能再惹他们
but we mustn't upset them in any other way.
大使提到了圣乔治岛
The ambassador mentioned St George's Island.
噢 真的?      世界那头出什么事了?
Oh, really?       What's going on in that part of the world?
世界哪头?
What part of the world?
那头 圣乔治岛那头
That part. The part where St George's Island is.
那是哪头?
What part is that?
如果你不知道 汉弗莱 建议你看看地图
I suggest you go and have a look at the map!
不 我知道 首相
No, I do know, Prime Minister.
好 那我们都知道了
Good. Then we both know.
白宫担心它会被马克思主义者接管
The White House is worried it might be taken over by Marxists.
这不好笑 汉弗莱
It's not funny, Humphrey.
对 不好笑 很感人 真的
No, indeed. Rather touching, really.
首相 一旦您开始干预
Prime Minister, once you start interfering
别国内部争端
in the internal squabbles of other countries,
您就岌岌可危了
you're on a very slippery slope.
外交部长刚这么说过
That's what the Foreign Secretary said.
真奇怪
Extraordinary.
还有今晚联合国对以色列的投票
Then there's the U.N. vote on Israel tonight.
美国要我们弃权
The Americans want us to abstain.
这是对阿拉伯关系问题
It's a question of maintaining our relationship with the Arabs.
伊斯兰政权
The power of Islam.
石油供应
Oil supplies.
汉弗莱 我在说是非问题
I'm talking about what's right and wrong.
可别让外交部听到
Well, don't let the Foreign Office hear you.
如果您非要不偏不倚
If you insist on an even-handed approach,
外交部可能同意弃权
the Foreign Office might agree to abstaining,
只要您授权我们在那的人
so long as you authorise our man there
公开发言抨击犹太复国主义
to make a powerful speech attacking Zionism.
我们当然要发扬和平 和谐 善意吧
Surely we should promote peace, harmony, goodwill.
那就很奇怪了
Well, it would be most unusual.
联合国是公认的
The U.N. is the accepted forum
表达国际憎恶的平台
for the expression of international hatred.
捍卫圣乔治岛的民主呢?
And defending democracy on St George's?
如果会伤害友邦 殃及英国利益 那就免了
Not if it harms us by upsetting our friends.
汉弗莱 难道英国不该支持法律和正义?
Britain should not support law and justice?
当然应该 首相
Of course we should. Prime Minister.
只要不影响外交政策就行
We just shouldn't let it affect our foreign policy, that's all.
我们应该锄强扶弱
We must fight for the weak against the strong.
那派军队去阿富汗对抗俄国啊
Then send troops to Afghanistan to fight the Russians.
俄国强过头了
The Russians are too strong.
那法律和正义呢?
What was that about law and justice?
尽管如此 汉弗莱 我想要向圣乔治岛民选首相保证
I want assurances sent to the Prime Minister of St George's Island
英国会支持他的
that Britain will stand by him.
与外交部长讨论吧
Discuss this with the Foreign Secretary.
谢谢 汉弗莱
Thank you, Humphrey.
谢谢 首相       你真帮了大忙
Thank you, Prime Minister.        You've been a great help
伯纳?      在 首相
Bernard?        Yes, Prime Minister?
圣乔治岛到底在哪?
Where exactly is St George's Island?
看看地球仪吧?
Shall we look at the globe?
私人办公室有一个      好主意
There is one in the private office.        Good idea.
下午好 路克      下午好 首相
Good afternoon, Luke.        Good afternoon, Prime Minister.
在哪呢?
Now, where is it?
在这儿 阿拉伯海      接近波斯湾
It's here, in the Arabian Sea.        Near the Persian Gulf.
西方的生命线
The lifeline of the West.
这是阿富汗 由苏维埃控制
There's Afghanistan, now under Soviet control.
阿拉伯海以北400英里
Only 400 miles north of the Arabian Sea.
如果苏维埃夺取巴基斯坦... 他们不会的
If the Soviets ever took Pakistan...Which they wouldn't.
如果会 他们就控制了波斯湾
If they did, they'd control the Persian Gulf,
阿拉伯海 印度洋
the Arabian Sea and the Indian Ocean.
他们一直都想要个"温水港"
They've always wanted a ''warm water port''.
他们不会入侵巴基斯坦
They wouldn't invade Pakistan.
美国有舰队永久驻扎
The Americans have a fleet permanently stationed here.
印度洋
The Indian Ocean.
首相 能和您说说...国内事务吗?
Prime Minister, may I have a word about...home affairs?
国内事务?      是的
Home affairs?        Yes.
不能等等吗? 我们在讨论外交事务
Can`t you wait? We're discussing foreign affairs.
不 首相 事情紧急
No, Prime Minister, it's rather urgent.
你没事吧 伯纳?
Are you all right, Bernard?
没事 首相 求您
Yes, Prime Minister. Please.
好吧 失陪 路克
Very well. Excuse me, Luke.
到底什么事?
What on earth's the matter?
我不想不忠诚
I don't want to be disloyal,
但当着路克的面
but it wasn't a good idea to continue that conversation
谈这些不好 安全问题
in front of Luke. Security.
他是你的同事 我的私人秘书之一
He's your colleague, one of my private secretaries.
军情六处干什么吃的?
What is MI6 up to...?
不是那种问题 他为外交部工作
Not that sort of risk. He works for the F.O.
他为我工作
He works for me.
没错 但他不仅是外交部派给你的人
Eh.yes, but he's not only your man from the Foreign Office,
他也是10号里他们的人
he's also their man in Number 10.
安插进来的
He's a plant.
您明白吗?      明白 不明白
Do you understand?        Yes. No!
你是说外交部有事瞒我?      是的
The F.O. is keeping something from me?        Yes.
什么事?      不知道 他们也没告诉我
What?        I don't know. They're keeping it from me, too.
那你又怎么知道的?      我不知道
Then how do you know?        I don't know.
你刚说外交部有事瞒我
You just said the F.O. was keeping something from me.
若你不知道 你又怎么知道?
How do you know if you don't know?
我不知道具体是什么
I don't know specifically what,
但我知道他们对所有人瞒着所有事
but I do know they always keep everything from everybody.
是惯例      那谁知道?
It's normal practice.        Who does know?
我来理清问题好吗?
May I just clarify the question?
您问谁知道那些我不知道
You are asking who would know what it is that I don't know
您也不知道 但外交部知道
and you don't know but the F.O. know that they know
他们不让您知道
that they are keeping from you
所以您不知道
so you don't know and they do know
我们只知道他们瞒着我们
all we know is there is something we don't know
而我们需要知道
and we want to know,
但我们不知道是什么的事 对吗?
but we don't know what because we don't know? Is that it?
我来理清吧
May I clarify the question?
除了外交部 还有谁知道外交部的秘密?
Who knows Foreign Office secrets apart from the Foreign Office?
这简单 只有俄国
Oh, that's easy. Only the Kremlin.
圣乔治岛的事真令人厌烦
This bother about St George's Island is getting to be a bore.
20年前我们让他们独立 就是一大错误
We made the real mistake giving them their independence.
大势所趋吧 变革的洪流之类?
Wasn't that right? Wind of change and all?
对 不过方式错了 当初应该分割那个岛
Yes, but not that way. We should have partitioned the island.
就像我们分割印度 塞浦路斯 巴勒斯坦 爱尔兰?
Like we did in India, Cyprus and Palestine? And Ireland?
没错 那是我们一贯的殖民地独立政策
Yes, that was our invariable practice with the colonies.
从未失效
It always worked.
分割国家不是总引起内战吗?
But didn't partition always lead to civil war?
像印度 塞浦路斯 巴勒斯坦和爱尔兰那样
As in India, Cyprus, Palestine and Ireland.
没错 但也使他们有事可做
Yes, but it kept them busy.
不与其他国家打仗 自己同自己打
Instead of fighting other people, they fought each other.
对 挺好的 省得我们定政策 干杯
Yes, rather good. Saved us having a policy. Cheers.
汉弗莱爵士      嗯 伯纳?
Sir Humphrey?        Yes, Bernard?
Um, Sir Humphrey...        Yes, Bernard?
能谈谈吗?      好的 伯纳
Could I have a word?        Yes, Bernard?
和你们俩      好 什么事?
With both of you.        Yes. What about?
圣乔治岛      又怎么了?
St George's.        What now?
貌似首相完全不了解情况
The PM seems to be completely in the dark.
好      非常好 还有什么?
Good.        Excellent. Anything else?
我在想 是不是有什么事他不知道?
I wonder, is there anything he doesn't know?
我都不知从哪说起 伯纳
I hardly know where to begin, Bernard.
不 我是说重要的事
No, I mean anything important.
外交部长会告诉他的
He has the Foreign Secretary to tell him.
他好像觉得外交部长也不全知道
He seems to think he doesn't know either.
那可不是
I should hope not!
你是在暗示首相应该知道吗?
Are you implying that he ought to know what is happening?
他是首相啊
Well, he is the Prime Minister.
对 可是伯纳 让政客
Bernard, it's simply too dangerous to let politicians
参与外交太危险了
become involved with diplomacy.
外交旨在存活到下世纪
Diplomacy is about surviving until the next century.
政治旨在存活到星期五下午
Politics is about surviving to the Friday afternoon!
世界上有157个独立国家
There are 157 independent countries in the world.
我们和他们打了多年交道了
We've dealt with them for years.
几乎全体议员都对此一窍不通
There's hardly an MP who knows anything.
给他们张世界地图
Show them a map of the world,
大多数人连怀特岛都找不到(英国南部)
most have a job finding the Isle of Wight.
政客不会这么无知吧?
Surely politicians can't be that ignorant?
非常好 坐下 伯纳
Very well. Sit down, Bernard.
上伏塔在哪?(西非伏塔河上游)      嗯
Where is the Upper Volta?       Em...
乍得的首都叫什么?      嗯
What's the capital of Chad?        Um...
马里的官方语言是什么?      嗯
What language do they speak in Mali?        Em...
秘鲁的总统是谁?      嗯
Who's the president of Peru?       Um...
喀麦隆信奉什么国教?
What is the national religion of Cameroon?
嗯      伯纳?
Em...        Bernard?
你应该参选议员
You should stand for Parliament.
不 我是说在我们民主国家
No, what I mean is if it's a democracy,
大家难道不讨论吗?
shouldn't people sort of discuss things a bit?
当然 充分讨论       不参考事实吗?
Of course. Full discussion.        And have the facts?
当然不!
Of course not!
他们不需要 事实只会把问题搞复杂
They don't want them. Facts complicate things.
媒体 人民和他们选的领袖
All the press, the people and their elected leaders
只想知道谁好谁坏
want to know is who are the goodies and baddies.
问题是为了国家利益
The interests of Britain nearly always involve doing
总得和人们认为的坏人做交易
deals with people they think are baddies.
以及偶尔抛弃不合作的好人
And not helping the goodies occasionally.
所以我们避免讨论外交事务
So we avoid discussion of foreign affairs.
或者只在外交部之内讨论
Or rather we keep it inside the Foreign Office
只制定一项政策 提交外交部长
then we produce one policy for the Foreign Secretary,
那就是我们的结论
which is our considered view.
他照办
And he can act upon it.
没有其他选择?没有备选方案?      没有
No options? No alternatives?        None.
如果他不满意呢?
What if he's not satisfied?
要是他敦促 我们会再看看
If pressed, we look at it again.
并得出另一结论?
And come up with a different view?
当然不是 同一结论
Of course not! We come up with the same view.
要是他非要选择呢?      显然 伯纳
What if he demands options?        It's obvious.
外交部会给他三个选择
The F.O. present him with three options,
其中两个实际上完全一样
two of which are, in fact, exactly the same.
第三个则完全不能接受
And the third is totally unacceptable.
比如轰炸华沙或入侵法国
Like bombing Warsaw or invading France.
有时我们鼓励外交部长
We occasionally encourage the Foreign Secretary to
自己出政策
produce his own policy,
然后告诉他不出48小时
then we tell him it will inevitably lead to World War Three,
那必将引发第三次世界大战
perhaps within 48 hours.
知道了 我真笨 对不起
I see. I'm sorry to appear stupid...
说哪里话 伯纳
Oh, perish the thought, Bernard.
可据我经验 大臣很在乎
In my experience, ministers are concerned about
政策对国内政治意见的影响
the effect of policy on domestic opinion.
这个体系似乎不允许这样
Our system doesn't seem to allow for that.
当然不 我们关注全球
Of course not. We take the global view.
以世界利益为准
We ask what's best for the world.
多数大臣关心会怎么说
Most ministers would ask what will the ''Daily Mail'' say!
伯纳 我们不能把外交政策
We can't have foreign policy made by yobbos
交给报界编辑或后座议员这类流氓
like Fleet Street editors or backbench MPs!
或内阁大臣      或内阁大臣
Or Cabinet ministers.        Or Cabinet ministers.
我们作正确决定
We take the right decisions
让他们解决政治问题
and let them sort out the politics later.
谁? 好的 请进 惠特莫夫人 谢谢
Yes? Yes, come in, Mrs Whitmore. Thank you.
如果外交部长不接受外交部的意见...?
If the Foreign Secretary won't accept this...?
这是个自由国度 他总可以辞职
It's a free country. He can always resign.
怎能这么对首相?
How can you treat the PM like this?
他当然担心圣乔治岛
Surely he is right to worry about St George's IS.
毕竟那是个民主国家
After all, It is the democracy!
很快就不是了
Not for long.
这是最新的电报
This is the fresh telegram.
东也门正筹备入侵
The East Yemen are preparing to invade
以支援左翼游击队
in support of the Marxist guerrillas.
真糟糕      是也不是
That's awful.        Yes and no.
对圣乔治政府糟透了
It is moderately bad news for the government of St George's,
但对游击队很好
but very good for the guerrillas.
那岛民怎么办?
What about the islanders?
伯纳 你说话像个政客
Bernard, you're reacting like a politician.
对不起 但我们怎么帮他们?      什么都不做
What are we going to do to help them?        Nothing.
要是他们请求我们呢?
What if St George's appeals to us?
我们给他们一切支持 除了帮忙
We'll give them every support, short of help.
要是首相非要帮助?
What if the Prime Minister insists that we help them?
那就遵从"四阶战术"
Then we follow the four-stage strategy.
是什么?
What's that?
外交部标准危机应对策略
The standard F.O. response in a time of crisis.
第一阶段 我们宣称什么事都没有
In stage one we say nothing is going to happen.
第二阶段 说也许有事发生 但我们不该采取行动
Stage two, it may happen, but we should do nothing.
第三阶段 说也许应该行动
Stage three, maybe we should do something about it,
但我们什么都做不了
but there's nothing we can do.
第四阶段 说也许当初能做点什么
Stage four, maybe there was something we could have done,
但现在已太迟了
but it's too late now.
下午的电报 首相
Afternoon telegrams, Prime Minister.
谢谢 路克
Thank you, Luke.
伯纳在哪?       他在汉弗莱爵士那
Where's Bernard?        I think he's with Sir Humphrey.
东也门有部队调动?       并不严重
Troop movements in East Yemen?        It's not significant.
美国大使提过东也门
The American ambassador mentioned it.
真的? 他竟然还听说过
Really? I'm surprised he'd heard of it.
他们要做什么?
What are they up to?
只是准备对西也门进行常规侵略
Just preparing a regular raid on West Yemen.
我们没什么好担心的?
Nothing for us to worry about?
完全不必担心 首相
Nothing at all.  Prime Minister
他还提到了圣乔治岛
He said something about St George's, too.
真的? 真有学问
Really? Educated man.
作为美国人
For an American.
那边有问题吗?
Is there a problem there?
不不 首相 常规内部争议
No, no, no. Prime Minister,Just the normal local squabbles.
他担心共产党会接管
He seems worried about a Communist take it over.
美国人总是担心
Americans always are.
路克 你看过这个吗?
Luke! Have you read this?
我们昨晚在联合国投票反对以色列
We voted against Israel in the U.N. last night!
看过 首相
Yes, Prime Minister.
但我明确指示要弃权的
But I gave express instructions to abstain.
不会吧 首相
I think not. Prime Minister
我明明告诉外交部长 我强烈认为我们不该偏袒
I said I felt very strongly that we should not take sides.
外交部长知道您的强烈看法
The Foreign Secretary noted your feeling.
但没照办
But did nothing about it!
恕我直言 首相 他办了
With respect, Prime Minister, he did.
他问了我们的联合国大使是否该考虑弃权
He asked our U.N. ambassador if we should consider abstaining.
大使怎么答复?      他说不行
What did he do?        He said no.
你是说外交部可以
You mean the Foreign Office can simply
忽略首相的意愿?
ignore the Prime Minister?
当然不 首相 不
Certainly not, Prime Minister. No.
他们作决定时会充分考虑您的意见
They take full account of you when coming to their decision,
但事情发展太快
but events move rapidly.
我们与阿拉伯关系中有些重要因素
There were important factors in our relationship with the Arabs
您昨晚考虑时并不知情
that were not known to you when you took your view.
我们没法及时通知您
We couldn't get through to you in time.
我有电话的
I am on the phone, you know.
我们觉得没有重要到值得在凌晨3点打扰您
It wasn't sufficiently important to wake you at 3 am.
非常重要 白宫会大发雷霆的
It was extremely important! The White House will do its nut!
本来可以每次联合国投票前都打电话通知您
You could be telephoned before every U.N. vote,
但他们开会时每晚投票两三次
but there are two or three a night.
我怎样才能扭转局势?
What can I do to reverse this?
什么都不做 首相 不然就尴尬了
Nothing. That would be most embarrassing.
政府政策一经陈述 便不容撤消
Once stated, policy can't be retracted.
路克 我要与以色列大使谈谈
I'd like to talk to the Israeli ambassador.
不要 首相
I think not, Prime Minister.
我要与以色列大使谈谈
I want to talk to the Israeli ambassador.
恕我直言 首相 这太不明智了
If I may say so, it would be rather unwise.
路克 能听见我说话吗? 看着我的嘴
Luke! Can you hear me? Watch my lips!
我想与以色列大使谈谈
I want to talk to the Israeli ambassador!
当然 首相 如果您一定要的话
Of course, Prime Minister, if that is your wish.
我会联系外交部长和理查爵士
I will contact the Foreign Secretary and Sir Richard
然后打电话给以色列...
and then telephone the Israeli...
我不想找外交部长和理查爵士
I don't want the Foreign Secretary and Sir Richard!
我只想见大使
I just want the ambassador
首相 绕开外交部长
Prime Minister, it would be most improper to see
单独见他太不合适了
him without the Foreign Secretary present.
为什么? 你以为我要谈什么?
Why? What do you think I want to talk to the ambassador about?
大概是联合国的投票
Presumably the vote at the U.N.
是吗? 那就不合适了      哦
Really? That would be most improper.        Oh.
我女儿露茜想找个
My daughter Lucy wishes to spend her
以色列集体农场渡假
next long vacation on a kibbutz.
或者说 除了苏塞克斯大学
Or I should say, as she's at the University of Sussex,
另一个集体农场
another kibbutz.
知道了      我们在伦敦政经学院是同学
I see.        The ambassador and I were at the LSE.
我想邀他今晚来我家喝酒
I thought I'd invite him to the flat tonight for a drink.
大约6点 请你安排一下 路克?
6 pm will be convenient. See to it, would you, Luke?
好的 首相      谢谢
Yes, Prime Minister.        Thank you.
别生气 吉姆 这经常发生
Don't be upset, Jim. It happens all the time.
我说了要弃权
I told them to abstain.
众所周知 在英国外交部
It's well known that in the British Foreign Office
首相发的指示
an instruction from the Prime Minister
会被外交部长转成请求
becomes a request from the Foreign Secretary,
国务大臣转成推荐
a recommendation from the Minister of State
到大使那就成了建议
and, finally, a suggestion to the ambassador.
如果它能走那么远
If it ever gets that far.
谢谢 干杯
Thank you. L'Chaim.
干杯
Cheers.
吉姆 你要怎么处理圣乔治岛的事?
Well, Jim, what are you going to do about St George's?
你也知道?      当然
You know about that?        Obviously.
没什么大问题吧, 是吗?
Not a serious problem, is it?
你的情报自然比我的好
it isn`t,yes.Your information must be better than mine.
我的来自外交部
Mine comes from the Foreign Office.
以色列情报处说
Israeli Intelligence says
东也门最近几天会
that East Yemen are going to invade
入侵圣乔治岛
St George's Island in the next few days.
什么?
What?!
原来是这样
So that's the connection.
你的外交部与东也门达成协议
Your Foreign Office agreed with East Yemen
他们会表面采取强硬外交手段
that they'll make strong diplomatic representations,
但实际什么也不做
but do nothing.
回报是 东也门接管圣乔治岛后维持机场合约
In return, you keep your airport contract.
会有骚乱的
There will be uproar!
但那只是开始
That's only the start.
驻华盛顿大使恰好告诉我
I happen to know from our ambassador in Washington
美国将会支援
the Americans are going to support
圣乔治现任政府
the present government of St George's .
在联合国...?      不 在战争中 在岛上
In the U.N...?        No, in battle. On St George's Island.
他们将派遣一个空降师进岛
They are sending an airborne division
第七舰队做后援
backed up by the Seventh Fleet.
美国侵略一个英联邦国家?
The American is invading a Commonwealth country?
皇室会勃然大怒 我会出足洋相
The Palace will hit the roof. And I'll look ridiculous.
美国为何不告诉我?      他们不信任你
Why didn't they tell me?        They don't trust you.
为什么？
Why not？
因为你相信外交部
Because you trust the Foreign Office.
哦, 是这样. 我能怎么做?
Oh, I see. What can I do about it?
吉姆 你在德国有支空降军队待命
Jim, you have an airborne battalion on standby in Germany
现在不需参加北约演习
that is not now needed for the NATO exercise.
你怎么知道?      我就是知道
How do you know?        I know.
如果你把他们派到圣乔治岛
Now, if you were to send it to St George's Island,
必能吓退东也门
it would frighten off East Yemen.
他们绝不敢入侵
They'd never dare invade.
当然 不该由以色列大使
Of course, it's not for the Israeli ambassador
给英国首相提建议
to advise the British Prime Minister.
首相也不会采纳你的建议
And he wouldn't take your advice anyway.
找外交部长和国防部长
Get me the Foreign Secretary and the Defence Secretary.
我在想外交部为何没有掩护自己
I wonder why the Foreign Office didn't cover themselves.
也许他们有
Maybe they did.
今晚他们给了我几箱文件
They gave me several boxes tonight.
除了这个我都看了
I've been through them all except this one.
我想会不会就是这个
I wonder if this could be it.
"北印度洋形势报告"
''Northern Indian Ocean Situation Report''.
有138页 就是它了
It's 138 pages. It must be it.
喂? 是的 罗尼
Hello? Yes, Ronnie.
我要圣乔治岛总统
I want the president of St George's Island to
邀请一支英国空降军队
invite Britain to send an airborne battalion
进行善意访问
on a goodwill visit.
不 只是表示友好 善意的
No, just a friendly gesture. Goodwill.
好 请马上办 谢谢
Yes, at once, please. Thank you.
他好像认为一次善意访问
He seemed to think that 800 fully-armed paratroopers
派800名全副武装的伞兵太多了
was an awful lot to send on a goodwill visit.
不 我们善意太多了
No, it's just an awful lot of goodwill.
对 保罗 你有支空降军队
Oh, yes, Paul. You know you have an airborne battalion
在德国待命?
on standby in Germany?
我怎么知道的不重要
Never mind how I know.
既然现在没任务
Well, since it's not being used,
我想让他们马上飞到圣乔治岛
I want them to fly straight off to St George's Island.
大概在非洲和印度之间
Sort of between Africa and India.
善意访问 只打一下旗帜
A goodwill visit. Just showing the flag.
邀请已经发出了 对 6小时后出发
They have been invited. Yes. Leave in...six hours.
对 临时善意访问
Yes, an instant goodwill visit.
让宣传办马上发布消息
Tell your press office to announce it at once.
不不 不要提到我 只是常规访问
No, no, leave me out of it. A routine visit.
好吧 一次常规的惊喜访问
All right. A routine surprise visit.
就说他们早就得到邀请
Well, say they were invited earlier,
只是北约演习耽误了行程
but the NATO exercise got in the way.
现在完事了 他们就来了
Now they're not needed, they're going.
没关系 没人知道是假的
All right. Nobody knows it's not true.
媒体发消息又不用宣誓
Press statements aren't delivered under oath.
他们午夜就出发
They'll be off at midnight.
我听说空中有支空降军队
I gather that there's an airborne battalion in the air.
那不是正好嘛
Sounds like the right place for it
我听说它正飞向圣乔治岛
I gather it's on its way to St George's.
对 2小时内就该到了
Yes, it should land in two hours time.
会不会太突然了?
Isn't this all rather sudden?
我突然有表示友好的冲动 汉弗莱
I had a sudden friendly impulse. Humphrey
我想传播一点善意
I wanted to spread a little goodwill.
今早外交部可没多少善意
There's not much goodwill in the F.O. this morning
真的 为什么?
Really? Why not?
这可以理解为挑衅
It might be construed as provocative,
派遣一支全副武装的空降军队
sending a fully-armed airborne battalion
进入一个爆炸性地区
into a trouble spot like that, an explosive situation.
爆炸性? 你不是说没问题嘛
Explosive? I thought there was no problem there.
是没有 真的
Eh...well, yes, indeed.
没问题 但有潜在的爆炸性
There is no problem, but it's explosive potentially.
为什么?      调遣军队总有潜在爆炸性
Why?        Moving troops is always potentially explosive.
在索尔兹伯里平原(英格兰)调来调去
We move them around Salisbury Plain.
也有潜在爆炸性?
Is that potentially explosive?
有很多未爆弹在...
There are a lot of unexploded shells on...
谢谢 伯纳
Thank you, Bernard.
请告诉我外交部担心什么
Do tell me why the Foreign Office is worried.
我很感兴趣
I'm fascinated.
这是个敏感地区 不稳定
It's a sensitive part of the world. Unstable.
他们总告诉我非常稳定
They always tell me how stable it is.
对 它确实...很稳定
Well, yes, indeed it is...very,
但那是种...不稳定的稳定
but it's a sort of...unstable sort of stability.
打扰了 汉弗莱爵士      什么事 路克?
Excuse me, Sir Humphrey.        Yes, Luke.
外交部的电报 首相
Foreign Office telegrams. Prime Minister.
谢谢 路克 天 还真多
Thank you, Luke. Oh, gosh. Rather a lot.
是的 对圣乔治岛的
Yes, the somewhat unorthodox visit
非正统访问有结果了
to St George's has stirred things up.
啊 东也门把部队调回基地了
Ah, I see East Yemen is moving its troops back to base.
是的 首相
Yes, Prime Minister.
又不想入侵西也门了?
Decided not to invade West Yemen after all?
好像是      太好了
So it seems.        Oh, this is nice.
美国对我们的小访问感到高兴 不错嘛
The Americans are delighted by our visit. That's good.
非常好 首相
Excellent, Prime Minister.
他们说若需要巩固
They say they are going to hold airborne division ready
他们有一整个空降师待命
if we want reinforcements.
巩固什么?
Reinforcements of what?
巩固善意 汉弗莱
Reinforcements of goodwill, Humphrey.
首相 请问您为何要搞这种恶作剧?
May I inquire where the impulse for this little escapade came from?
当然可以 路克提议的      路克?
Of course you may. It came from Luke.        Luke?!
我?
From me?
是你起草了那份
It was you who put together that
精彩的"北印度洋形势报告" 对吗?
masterly Northern Indian Ocean Situation Report, wasn`t it?
对 可论点是什么都不用做
Yes, but it argued for not doing anything.
得啦 路克 你骗不了我      什么?
Come off it, Luke. You can't fool me.        What?!
我能体会言外之意
I can read between the lines.
有些政治家对外交有直觉
Some politicians have a feeling for foreign affairs.
我知道你是说圣乔治岛需要支援
I knew you meant St George's needed support.
对 呃 其实不是的
Oh, yes. Well, no, actually.
只在107页有一段
Only in one paragraph on page 107.
足够了 我明白这个暗示
It was enough. I can take the hint.
我全归功于你
I'm giving you full credit for it.
我告诉外交部长是你提醒的
I told the Foreign Secretary it was your warning sparked it off.
不不 不是的 您不会吧?
No, no, it wasn't You haven't?
你当然也猜到了
And I don't think I'm giving away any secrets
一定会报答你的
when I say you are going to be rewarded.
报答?      任命你为一个重要使馆的大使
Rewarded?        Ambassador at a very important embassy.
哪个使馆?      特拉维夫
Which embassy?        Tel Aviv.
天哪 您不能派我去以色列
Oh, my God! You can't send me to Israel.
想想我的前途
Think about my career.
别傻了 这是荣誉 是晋升
Don't be absurd. It's an honour. Promotion.
但以色列人会不高兴的
Yse, it will upset Israelis.
他们不喜欢我
They won't want me.
他们知道我是阿拉伯那边的
They know I'm on the Arab side.
我以为你是我们这边的
I thought you were on our side.
当然 可是...
Of course, yes, but...
我们需要你这样的人去特拉维夫
We need somebody like you in Tel Aviv
解释我们为何在联合国投票反对他们
to explain why we always vote against them in the UN.
不是么? 汉弗莱?
Don't we, Humphrey?
是 首相
Yes, Prime Minister.
破烂熊字幕组 -==www.RagBear.com==-